Paul James Wright

CONTACT INFORMATION Rm 614, Kelvin Building University of Glasgow Glasgow, G12 8QQ United Kingdom Work: +44 (0)14133 08855 Web: www.pauljwright.co.uk Email: paul.wright@glasgow.ac.uk Publication List: SAO/NASA ADS

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My interests range from stellar to solar physics; my main interests lie in the heating of the solar atmosphere, including active regions and loops. I have expertise in the analysis of spectroscopic and narrowband Extreme Ultra-Violet (EUV) and X-ray data from *SDO* and *Hinode*, in addition to the hard X-ray (HXR) imaging/spectroscopic observations from *NuSTAR*'s heliophysics campaign. Furthermore, I am currently investigating the modelling of coronal loop light-curves using the EBTEL (Enthalpy-Based Thermal Evolution of Loops) hydrodynamics code with particular interest in the weak bremmstrahlung components, and the relevance for future soft to hard X-ray instruments and missions.

EDUCATION

University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK

2014 – present (expected early 2018)

Ph.D. Solar Physics

Thesis Topic: *The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings* Advisers: Dr Iain G. Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

University of Southampton, Southampton, UK

2010 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

First-class honours (1:1) Adviser: Professor Malcolm Coe

Harvard University/Harvard-Smithsonian CfA, Cambridge, MA, USA

2013 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

Thesis Topic: Superflare Rates of Solar-Like Stars Advisers: Dr Steven H. Saar, Dr Jeremy J. Drake

CURRENT ACADEMIC APPOINTMENT

APPOINTMENTS

PREVIOUS ACADEMIC

Affiliate Staff Member, University of Glasgow SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

2017 – present

Post-Graduate Research Assistant, University of Glasgow

2014 - 2017

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

Project: The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings

- Analysed observations of the Sun with *NuSTAR*, a telescope not designed for heliophysics. These observations are the most sensitive of their kind and have resulted in numerous, wide-ranging highly-collaborative peer-reviewed publications.
- Analysed non-flaring coronal time-series in pursuit of signatures of the coronal heating mechanism. Techniques included time-lag analysis (cross-correlation), Fourier analysis, wavelet analysis, and local intermittency measure (LIM).
- Studied the temperature distribution of the solar atmosphere through the recovery of an ill-posed inverse problem (the differential emission measure, DEM) using techniques such as Tikhonov regularisation, Markov chain Monte Carlo, and sparsity.
- The press-release image produced from the *NuSTAR* observations obtained for Wright *et al.* 2017 was published by numerous news outlets, and is one of the five iconic images from *NuSTAR*'s first five years in space.

Collaborators: Dr Iain Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

Visiting Researcher, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC)

2016

Heliophysics Science Division

• Worked on the possibility of implementing DEM maps in the Helioviewer project, and their usefulness as an input for various established analysis techniques.

Collaborators: Dr Nicholeen Viall, Dr Jack Ireland

Research Scholar, Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA)

2013 - 2014

Solar and Stellar X-Ray Group

- Designed and implemented a sophisticated stellar flare detection routine for long-cadence (30 mins) *Kepler* data obtained from a proprietary set of spectroscopically verified solar-type stars in three open clusters.
- A preliminary version of this work had coverage by Science, and The Smithsonian Magazine.

Collaborators: Dr Steven Saar, Dr Søren Meibom, Dr Jeremy Drake, Dr Vinay Kashyap

Paul James Wright

Previous	Summer Researcher, University of Southampton	2013	
ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS (CONT.)	 Astronomy Group Investigated the presence of double blue straggler sequences in globular clusters using Hubble Space Telescope (WFC3) data. Collaborators: <i>Dr Andrea Dieball</i> 		
REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS	[1] Marsh, A. J., Smith, D. M., Glesener, L. et al 2017. First NuSTAR Limits on Quiet Sun Hard X-Ray Transient Events, ApJ, 849, 131		
	[2] Wang, J., Simões, P. J. A., Jeffrey, N. L. S. et al 2017. Observations of Reconnection Flows in a Flare on The Solar Disk, ApJL, 847, L1		
	[3] Wright, P. J. , Hannah, I. G., Grefenstette, B. W., et al 2017. Microflare Heating of a Solar Active Region Observed with NuSTAR, Hinode/XRT, and SDO/AIA, ApJ, 844, 132		
	[4] Kuhar, M., Krucker, S., Hannah, I. G., et al 2017. Evidence of Significant Energy Input in the Late Phase of a Solar Flare from NuSTAR X-ray Observations, ApJ, 835, 6		
FIRST AUTHOR PUBLICATIONS IN PREPERATION	[5] Wright, P. J., Hannah, I. G., Viall, N. M., et al		
	[6] Wright, P. J., Saar, S. H., Meibom, S., et al		
Conferences,	Invited Oral Presentations		
WORKSHOPS, & SCHOOLS	ISSI Team Meeting: Coronal Nanoflares, Bern, CH Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA, USA	2016 2014	
	Oral/ePoster Presentations		
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII, Palermo, Sicily, IT	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA Hinode 10, Nagoya, JP	2016 2016	
	National Astronomy Meeting 2016, Nottingham, UK	2016	
	Hinode 9, Belfast, UK	2015	
	Glasgow-Cambridge Flare Workshop, Glasgow, UK	2015	
	Poster Presentations	2017	
	European Solar Physics Meeting (ESPM), Budapest, HU Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017 2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VII, Cambridge, UK	2015	
	NAM 2015, Llandudno, UK	2015	
	223rd AAS Meeting, National Harbor, MD, USA	2014	
	Schools Attended CESPA Partie Summer School 2015, Cleanery, LIV	2015	
	CESRA Radio Summer School 2015, Glasgow, UK STFC Advanced Summer School in Solar Physics, Dundee, UK	2015 2014	
	Conferences/Workshops Attended		
	NuSTAR Heliophysics Workshop (remote participation), Berkeley, CA, USA	2017	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2015	
	RAS Discussion Meeting: Results from IRIS, London, UK	2015	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK 1st Space Glasgow Research Conference, Glasgow, UK	2014 2014	
	The space Glasgon Research Conference, Clasgon, CI	2011	
AWARDS AND	University of Glasgow		
GRANTS TOTAL: £7000	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Student Poster Award	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Studentship Award Coronal Loops Workshop VIII Travel Award	2017 2017	
	National Astronomical Observatory of Japan Travel Award	2016	
	Hinode 9 Travel Award	2015	
	European Space Agency/Cambridge Philosophical Society Travel Award	2015	
	University of Southampton		
	Research Scholarship	2013	
	Summer Studentship Grant	2013	

Paul James Wright

TEACHING	Coursera Inc. "Data Scientists Toolbox" Community Mentor An invited mentor of a course in the Data Science specialization offered by Joh	2017 – present		
	An invited mentor of a course in the Data Science specialization offered by Johns Hopkins University (see professional development).			
	University of Glasgow	2016 2017		
	Astronomy 1 Tutorial Demonstrator Supervised students, and marked first-year astronomy problem sets.	2016 - 2017		
	Astronomy 3/4 (Honours) Laboratory Demonstrator	2015 - 2016		
	Demonstrated, supervised, and marked a number of final-year research project			
	such as asteroid light curves, and solar limb darkening.			
	Physics Pre-University Summer School Taught at a pre-university school for students entering first year.	2015		
Memberships	NuSTAR Heliophysics Working Group, Member	2015 – present		
	International Space Science Institute (ISSI), Young Scientist Member	2015 – present		
	Member of Paola Testa's ISSI Team: New Diagnostics of Particle Acceleration	in Solar Coronal		
	Nanoflares from Chromospheric Observations and Modeling	2014 mmagant		
	Royal Astronomical Society, RAS Fellow	2014 – present		
COMMUNITY	Nature Communications, Reviewer	2017 – present		
INVOLVEMENT	Glasgow Astronomy & Astrophysics Group Meeting, Organiser	2017		
	CESRA Radio Summer School, Volunteer Organiser	2015		
SCIENTIFIC	Glasgow Science Centre, Demonstrator	2016		
OUTREACH	British Science Week, Demonstrator	2016		
	Institute of Physics: Women and Girls in Science, Demonstrator	2016		
	Scottish Television (STV), Guest Presenter World Wide Telegraph Ambassador	2015 2013 – 2014		
	World Wide Telescope, Ambassador BBC Stargazing Live, Demonstrator	2013 – 2014		
	So'ton Astrodome, Demonstrator	2013		
	BBC Bang Goes The Theory Roadshow, Demonstrator	2012		
	UK Solar Physics (UKSP) Nuggets , concise, easy-to-read science articles 84. The first <i>NuSTAR</i> microflare	2017		
	Hinode/XRT Picture of the Week (XPOW)			
	The First Microflare Observations with <i>Hinode/XRT & NuSTAR</i>	2017		
Personal Projects	ColourBlind, A repository for colour-blind-friendly colour tables.			
Professional	Coursera, Inc. (MOOC Platform)			
DEVELOPMENT	Using Coursera.org, a massive open online course (MOOC) platform, to take specializations (a series of related courses and a final capstone project) offered by accredited universities to further develop skills and			
	understanding in a wide range of computer science topics.			
	Data Science, Johns Hopkins University	2017 – present		
	Nine-course (plus capstone) introduction to data science.	2017 mmagant		
	Mastering Software Development in R , Johns Hopkins University Four-course (plus capstone) specialization providing riguourous training in R.	2017 – present		
	Statistics with R , Duke University	2017 – present		
	Four-course (plus capstone) specialization providing further training in R, with entics.			
TECHNICAL SKILLS:	Computing: Python, R, IDL, ETeX, git, GitHub, Linux/Unix, Mac OSX, Microsoft Windows, Bash, Microsoft Office, Adobe Creative Cloud			
	<i>General:</i> Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Interdisciplinary Collaboration, Public Speaking, Statistics, Teaching, Writing (Technical & Lay)			

Teaching, Writing (Technical & Lay)